<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reviews on Alma Andersson</title>
    <link>https://example.org/categories/reviews/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reviews on Alma Andersson</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 06:01:05 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://example.org/categories/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Thesis Epilogue</title>
      <link>https://example.org/blog/2022-04-06-epilogue/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 06:01:05 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/blog/2022-04-06-epilogue/</guid>
      <description>An excerpt from the Epilogue of my PhD thesis. These are the lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt, the predictions I have, and the hopes I harbor.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paper Review | Visualizing Data using t-SNE</title>
      <link>https://example.org/blog/2021-02-20-tsne/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 10:53:05 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/blog/2021-02-20-tsne/</guid>
      <description>t-SNE is one of the most commonly used methods for dimensionality reduction in RNA-seq analysis, yet few people know how it actually works. Here we&amp;rsquo;ll walk through the original t-SNE paper by van der Maaten and Hinton; looking at the motivation behind it, the mathematics that fuel its power, and how to interpret its hyperparameters.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paper Review | Normalization and variance stabilization of single-cell RNA-seq data using regularized negative binomial regression</title>
      <link>https://example.org/blog/2021-01-31-nbreg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 12:47:31 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/blog/2021-01-31-nbreg/</guid>
      <description>For this bi-weekly paper review, my choice fell upon a paper that I&amp;rsquo;ve skimmed through multiple times before, but never gave the proper read-through it deserves. It was a definite given when I started to curate a list of papers that I wanted to include in this series of reviews. Not only do I find it to be an elegant and well-composed paper, but it has had nothing but an /imperative/ influence on the RNA-seq based analysis these last years.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paper Review | Toward a Common Coordinate Framework for the Human Body</title>
      <link>https://example.org/blog/2021-01-19-ccf-rev/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 15:01:37 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/blog/2021-01-19-ccf-rev/</guid>
      <description>For quite some while now, I&amp;rsquo;ve carried a slight sensation of guilt within me. Guilt for being so caught up in my own projects and activities that I&amp;rsquo;ve come to neglect one of the most essential duties as a researcher: to survey, read, and contemplate upon new (and old) material that have been published. It&amp;rsquo;s so easy to put that interesting paper aside in order to finish a project deadline, as no immediate gains are observed from reading through the former in contrast to completing the latter.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
