<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>traveling | almaan</title>
    <link>/tag/traveling/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/traveling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>traveling</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:53:05 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0976d26fdaec5d0ec6c053b09a4e039a_2013_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>traveling</title>
      <link>/tag/traveling/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I travel</title>
      <link>/post/2023-03-27-howitravel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:53:05 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2023-03-27-howitravel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every person has their own style of traveling reflecting their interests,
prioritize, budget, and physical abilities/limitations. I&amp;rsquo;ve had the privilege
to travel quite a lot during the last five years, usually by extending work
trips by a few days but sometimes just for pure pleasure. Most of these trips
have been solo but there are a few exceptions. When traveling with others, I
tend to adapt to their preferences, but when alone I have a fairly particular
way of operating: I tend to cover a lot of ground in a small amount of time and
also manage to keep the budget fairly low. These are some of my &amp;ldquo;hacks&amp;rdquo; or
lessons than I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt from my experiences, some of them apply to city trips,
others to nature ones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Move by your own means. You&amp;rsquo;ll get 10x the experience if you walk or bike
instead of taking uber/lyft/cabs or public transport. Walking is by far the
best way to &amp;lsquo;get to know&amp;rsquo; a place. However, if you need to go far and don&amp;rsquo;t want
to spend hours walking through boring neighborhoods, then use a bike. Most
larger cities have something to the equivalent of NYC&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Citibikes&amp;rdquo;, in the
US, you can usually use Lyft (at the time of writing) to find and unlock
bikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google maps is king. I can&amp;rsquo;t believe that this app is free, but it&amp;rsquo;s the one
thing I rely on beyond anything else. Before I go anywhere, I always download
the offline maps, which allows you to orient yourself without using data
(great for avoiding hefty roaming fees). If you&amp;rsquo;re a bit strategic, make a
&amp;ldquo;List&amp;rdquo; in google maps (by saving a place) of interesting things to see or
places to visit; by doing so it&amp;rsquo;s easier to plan your route or see if you&amp;rsquo;re
close to anything cool as you&amp;rsquo;re strolling through an area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mobile data. Life is &lt;em&gt;so much&lt;/em&gt; easier with when you can access information on
the web. If you&amp;rsquo;re traveling to a country where you&amp;rsquo;ll have to pay a roaming
charge, I&amp;rsquo;d suggest looking into either buying a &amp;ldquo;tourist sim card&amp;rdquo; or get a
virtual sim card (if your phone supports it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hydrate. Most people say they get &amp;ldquo;hangry&amp;rdquo;, but honestly, most times it&amp;rsquo;s a lack
of liquid that&amp;rsquo;s the culprit. If you walk a lot, especially in warm weather,
you sweat more than you realize. I rarely feel thirst, so it took me a while
to realize how much better the experience is once you properly hydrate. I try
to consume &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; 20 fl.oz. every &lt;em&gt;second hour&lt;/em&gt;. This works wonders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toilets. If your drink a lot, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to pee a lot and public restrooms
can offer some PTSD inducing sights. What I&amp;rsquo;ve found to work really well is:
Museums and Shopping malls. These restrooms tend to be: 1) free and 2) clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ditch the food search. Finding food takes a lot of time. I&amp;rsquo;m not someone who
travels for &amp;ldquo;the food experience&amp;rdquo;, if you&amp;rsquo;re a foodie then this tip will not
resonate will you, but if you&amp;rsquo;re ok with down-prioritizing food keep on
reading. Instead of going through the process of finding something to eat,
ordering, waiting for the food, etc. I tend to just bring one or two energy
bars alternatively, buy them on the fly. Sometimes I buy a bowl of fruit, a
yogurt, or some bread from a grocery store - depending on what I crave.
Paradoxically, for me, if I&amp;rsquo;m in motion I don&amp;rsquo;t get as hungry as when sitting
still (like at work). This presents a nice segue to my next tip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cutlery. I usually keep a pair of plastic cutlery (it&amp;rsquo;s biodegradable, don&amp;rsquo;t
worry) in my backpack. It sounds weird, but it&amp;rsquo;s great if you buy something
edible that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to eat with your hands (e.g., yogurt), a lot of
small stores don&amp;rsquo;t provide you with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
