<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alma Anderson | almaan</title>
    <link>/author/alma-anderson/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/alma-anderson/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Alma Anderson</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 11:05:04 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0976d26fdaec5d0ec6c053b09a4e039a_2013_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Alma Anderson</title>
      <link>/author/alma-anderson/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publication | Spatial Single Cell Mapping</title>
      <link>/post/stereoscope-001/initial-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 11:05:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/stereoscope-001/initial-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Delighted to say that our manuscript &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Single-cell and spatial transcriptomics
enables probabilistic inference of cell type topography&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is now published in
&lt;em&gt;Communications Biology&lt;/em&gt; and thus out there for everyone to read in its final
form. This is the paper that describes the theoretical underpinnings for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/almaan/stereoscope&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;stereoscope&lt;/a&gt;, which allows you to
spatial map cell types found in single cell data onto spatial transcriptomics
data. There is also a nice bit of discussion as to whether spatial
transcriptomics data (ST/Visium) can be properly modeled using a negative
binomial distribution (which we use) found in the supplementary (spoiler, it
seems like it). Have a look at it if you are interested!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manuscript Link : &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s42003-020-01247-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HERE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stereoscope Link : &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/almaan/stereoscope&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HERE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S: I&amp;rsquo;m also planning to update the code base in the future, providing an API for
&lt;code&gt;scanpy&lt;/code&gt;, but also add some features like subsampling and gene selection to the
standard modules; but that is for later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manuscript | Spatial Exploration of Her2 Breast Cancer</title>
      <link>/post/her2-001/initial-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 11:05:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/her2-001/initial-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve put out a new
&lt;a href=&#34;%22https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.07.14.200600v1.article-metrics%22&#34;&gt;manuscript&lt;/a&gt; on bioRxiv, where the expression landscape of HER2-positive
breast cancer tumors is studied from a spatial perspective. This study contains
several examples of how spatial data may be analyzed and what information beyond
the obvious - like the spatial distribution of a certain gene - that can be
mined from it. My hope is that anyone looking for ideas regarding how to analyze
their own spatial data find this useful and relevant, irregardles of their
interest in breast cancer. In the study we cluster spots by gene expression, but
also take this one step further, using the clusters to find &lt;i&gt;core
signatures&lt;/i&gt; of immune and tumor cell populations within our samples. We also
use &lt;i&gt;stereoscope&lt;/i&gt; to map single cell data down onto our tissue sections,
information which then is used to indentify potential TLS-sites as well as to
study patterns of cell type co-localization. All the scripts and a neat app for
visualization of the results can be found &lt;a href=&#34;%22https://github.com/almaan/her2st/%22&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resource | Formal systems in Biology</title>
      <link>/post/synt-bio-001/initial-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 10:05:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/synt-bio-001/initial-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Browsing through my daily feed, I stumbled upon
&lt;a href=&#34;%22https://github.com/prathyvsh/formal-systems-in-biology%22target=%22_blank%22&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
neat resource which lists (and links to) fundamental ideas that have shaped the
field of systems biology. To me, many of these publications represent some of
the earliest attempts to reduce complex biological systems and processes into
something simpler, more comprehensible, by viewing them through the lense of
mathematics; truly groundbreaking efforts that paved the way for the current
trends of ML/AI in biology. I&amp;rsquo;d strongly recommend anyone with an interest in
the field to have a look at it; something that contains work from both Alan
Turing and John von Neumann can&amp;rsquo;t be anything but good!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
