<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Notes on Alma Andersson</title>
    <link>https://almaan.github.io/categories/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Notes on Alma Andersson</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:53:05 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://almaan.github.io/categories/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Getting to work</title>
      <link>https://almaan.github.io/blog/2024-12-31-shuttle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:53:05 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://almaan.github.io/blog/2024-12-31-shuttle/</guid>
      <description>Three to four mornings a week, I walk to one of the Genentech shuttle buses, hop on, fall asleep, and wake up slightly disoriented as we arrive on campus. On the other days, I bike or run to work. To some extent this walk is a part of my routine, and when something becomes part of my routine I want to optimize it.&#xA;In this case optimization means that I want to find the time by which I should leave from home that:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I travel</title>
      <link>https://almaan.github.io/blog/2023-03-27-howitravel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:53:05 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://almaan.github.io/blog/2023-03-27-howitravel/</guid>
      <description>Every person has their own style of traveling reflecting their interests, prioritize, budget, and physical abilities/limitations. I&amp;rsquo;ve had the privilege to travel quite a lot during the last five years, usually by extending work trips by a few days but sometimes just for pure pleasure. Most of these trips have been solo but there are a few exceptions. When traveling with others, I tend to adapt to their preferences, but when alone I have a fairly particular way of operating: I tend to cover a lot of ground in a small amount of time and also manage to keep the budget fairly low.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
